A Guide to the Miscellaneous Letters and Documents Collection, 1824-2010
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Miscellaneous Letters and Documents Collection, 1824-2010
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-33
3 boxes, 5"x10.5"x15.5," 1.5 linear foot, 199 items
Historical Collections
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection is a compilation of letters and documents donated by different people over time to Historical Collections.
Historical Information
The letters and documents are a miscellaneous collection.
Scope and Content
The scope and content of the documents are diverse. This collection includes papers on the history of the Paul Goodloe McIntire Memorial Clinic, the development of the Otolaryngology Program at the University of Virginia School of Medicine, and women medical students at UVA in the 1920s. Also included are a letter from Rene Laennec, inventor of the stethoscope, and another from Carl Rokitansky, a famous pathologist. There is a series of letters from George W. Banks, a medical student in the 1890s; 1831 lecture notes on cholera and its treatment; examinations by the West Virginia Board of Examiners for Registered Nurses from the 1920s; the early 1900s daybook of Dr. J. E. Copeland; William P. Braxton's lecture cards from medical courses at the University of Pennsylvania in the 1830s; an account book kept by [Dr.?] Robert Gamble in the 1830s; two 19th century recipe books; and documents concerning Nuzhet O. Atuk and the beginning of hemodialysis at the University of Virginia Hospital.
Arrangement
The arrangement of the documents is dependent upon the time of their donation and processing.
Contents List
- "The Capsule," "Nurse Please!" Pictured by Jean McConnell, 1944-45, 1 TD mimeographed 6pp., 1 book with AN, 2 B&W photos 2.75" x 4.5", 2 AN (Box-folder 01-001)
  "The Capsule" is a University of Virginia newsletter for nurses. "Nurse Please!" was the property of Barbara Hughes Moore and includes drawings with the names of people from UVa written in. The photos are of unidentified people but included in the folder are 2 pieces of paper with the names of Barbara Hughes Moore and Ellen Stout.
- "History of the Paul Goodloe McIntire Memorial Clinic at the University of Virginia Hospital" by Zula Mae Baber, 1949 December, 2 TMs with AN 32pp., 1 TD with AN 1p. 1 card, 1 card in folder (Box-folder 01-002)
  The McIntire Memorial Clinic was the first tumour clinic in Virginia, and the precursor of the University's present Cancer Center.
- "Development of the Otolaryngology Program at The University of Virginia School of Medicine" by Robert W. Cantrell, M.D., 1980 January 13, 1 TMs 16pp. (Box-folder 01-003)
  This paper was presented at the 17th Annual Meeting of the Advisory Committee, University of Virginia Medical Alumni. Cantrell mentions, among others, Drs. Fletcher Woodward, G. Slaughter Fitz-Hugh, Robert A. Jahrsdoerfer, Michael Johns, W. Copley McLean, Edwin Rubel, and Roger Ruth.
- "The Out Patient Department, University of Virginia Hospital Charlottesville Virginia," 1950, 1 pamphlet (Box-folder 01-004)
- "The Notebook of Robley Dunglison, Student of Clinical Medicine in Edinburgh, 1815-1816" by Mary Jeanne A. Jones and Chalmers L. Gemmill, 1967, 1 journal article reprinted (Box-folder 01-005)
  Article is reprinted from "Journal of the History of Medicine and Allied Sciences"
- Letters from Nell Fuller to Myrl Ebert and from Nell Fuller to Minnie Orfanos, 1973 November 12, 29, 2 TL carbon copies 3pp. (Box-folder 01-006)
  Nell Fuller was Head of Technical Services at the Health Sciences Library.
- Letter from Frank L. Hereford to Jesse L. Fowler with enclosed resolution, 1976 August 20, 1 TL copy 1p., 1 resolution signed 1p., 1 AN 1p. (Box-folder 01-007)
  The resolution concerns the establishment of the Walter Merritt Seward Chair of Family Practice at UVa.
- Letter from George R. Minor to Mr. Kincaid, 1956 February 16, 1 TLS 1p. (Box-folder 01-008)
  Minor requests contributions for a portrait of Dr. "Ned" Lehman.
- Exam in Histology (Tuttle), 1897 March 18, 1 AN 1p. (Box-folder 01-009)
  This exam was found inserted in John T. Thornton's copy of "Notes on Anatomy" (1893) by William B. Towles. "Tuttle" is Albert H. Tuttle, Professor of Biology.
- Letter from Rene Laennec to a close friend and fellow physician, 1824, September 6, 1 ALS 1p. (Box-folder 01-010)
  This letter was sent from Quimper, Brittany, the birthplace of Laennec who invented the stethoscope in 1819. The letter concerns Laennec's shortened stay in Brittany and invites his friend to dinner to discuss medicine with other friends. He refers to having not been able to meet his friend at Kerlouarnec, the Laennec family estate in Ploare, near Douarnenez.
- Letter from Carl Rokitansky to ?, 1861, 1862, 1869, 3 ALS 5pp., 1 envelope (Box-folder 01-011)
  Rokitansky is a famous pathologist born in Koniggratz, Bohemia. He studied in Prague and Vienna.
- Letter from George W. Banks to his wife, 1894 November 4, 1 ALS 6pp., 1 envelope (Box-folder 01-012)
  Banks writes of the rigors of life as a medical student at UVa.
- Letter from George W. Banks to his wife, 1895 February 5, 1 ALS 1p. (Box-folder 01-013)
  Banks writes of his return trip and arriving in Basic at 6 A.M. (Basic City was an incorporated town in Augusta County that was eventually consolidated with Waynesboro.)
- Letter from George W. Banks to his wife, Genie, 1896 October 25, 1 ALS 8pp. (Box-folder 01-014)
  Banks writes from Baltimore, Maryland of his difficult exams in chemistry and materia medica.
- Letter from George W. Banks to his wife, Genie, 1896 November 8, 1 ALS 4pp. (Box-folder 01-015)
  Banks writes about his studies as well as a patient he is treating. He mentions McKinley's election and his desire to go to West Virginia, evidently as a doctor to work with miners.
- Letter from George W. Banks to his wife, Genie, 1896 November 15, 1 ALS 4pp. (Box-folder 01-016)
  Banks writes of having less respect for Republicans and "negroes" since the election. Says he will be the "white man's Dr."
- Letter from George W. Banks to his wife, Genie, 1896 November 22, 1 ALS 8pp. (Box-folder 01-017)
  Banks writes of medically helping a fellow boarder, praises the anatomy drill he got at the University of Virginia, says he is not worried about his studies and has been working hard.
- Letter from George W. Banks to his wife, 1897 March 14, 1 ALS 4pp., 1 envelope (Box-folder 01-018)
  Banks writes of studying and anticipates leaving the city soon. Mentions that people with syphilis go to hot springs to help the mercury soak into them.
- Letter from Mary and Dr. M. T. Reeder to Dr. and Mrs. George W. Banks, 1903 April 10, 1 ALS 3pp., 1 envelope (Box-folder 01-019)
  Dr. Reeder writes his cousin a sympathy letter on the occasion of the death of Banks' father who is Reeder's uncle.
- Check from the University of Virginia to R. C. Vandegrift & Son, 1887 September 1, 1 check signed (Box-folder 01-020)
- Doctor's bill from H. C. Hubbard to Mr. Thomas W. Crowder, 1851, 1 ADS 1p., 1 copy (Box-folder 01-021)
  The account lists bill for medicine as well as visits. Names as well as relationships of the patients are given.
- Prescription for Dr. Samuel S. Masters, N.D., 1 AMS 2p. (Box-folder 01-022)
  The prescription is for rheumatism.
- Letter from H. Holt to Mrs. O. C. Billings, 1844 May 29, 1 ALS 1p. (Box-folder 01-023)
  Holt gives medical advice for Mrs. Billings' sister. He sends pills to keep the bowels open and also advises drops. He suggests she use warm foot baths, or even better, warm hip baths; apply mustard poultices; and get non-fatiguing exercise.
- Class notes of M. B. Conrad, 1852-53, 1 AMS bound (Box-folder 01-024)
  Conrad was from Virginia and a medical student at the University of Pennsylvania.
- Invitation to Dr. William Graham to attend operation of Dr. Hugh T. Nelson at the Charlottesville Dispensary Annex, 1898 October 25, 1 ADS 2pp. (Box-folder 01-025)
- Lecture notes on cholera and its treatment, 1831, 2 AM 10pp. (Box-folder 01-026)
- Letter from Dr. Pennie to Mrs. T. L. Berney, 1827 May, 1 ALS 4pp. (Box-folder 01-027)
  Pennie congratulates Mrs. Berney on the birth of her baby and writes a prescription for a bowel complaint.
- Letter from G. N. Bliss to Dr. J. S. Davis (1824-85), 1865 November 7, 1 ALS 4pp., 1 copy, 1 transcript (Box-folder 01-028)
  Bliss was presumably a Union Officer in the Civil War. Davis treated him at Charlottesville Hospital and bliss thanks him for his kindness. The Rhode Island Historical Society has a collection of Civil War Military Records and includes the George N. Bliss Papers (MSS 298) and Soldiers and Sailors Historical Society Records (MSS 723). Bliss was a member of the First Regimental Rhode Island Cavalry.
- Sanitary Inspector's Report, Form K, 1864, 1 TD 8pp. (Box-folder 01-029)
- Forty-first examination of the West Virginia Board of Examiners for Registered Nurses, 1927 October 27, 1 TD 10pp. (Box-folder 01-030)
  The examination includes sections named pediatrics; practical; anatomy & physiology; bacteriology, hygiene, public health and sanitation; surgery & gynecology; obstetrics; history & ethics; medical nursing; dietetics; and materia medica, toxicology and chemistry
- Forty-second examination of the West Virginia Board of Examiners for Registered Nurses, 1928 April 16, 1 TD 8pp. (Box-folder 01-031)
  The examination includes sections named obstetrics and gynecology; materia medica, therapeutics and toxicology; surgery; history & ethics; pediatrics; dietetics; medical nursing; and bacteriology, hygiene, chemistry, and public health
- Sanders family vaccination and physical examination records, 1920-22, 1928, 1953, 6 TDS (Box-folder 01-032)
  Includes 1953 American National Red Cross membership card for Robert C. Sanders, a "Train Ticket to No-Diptheria town on the Health Road," and American Red Cross, Department of Nursing-Bureau of Public Health Nursing school inspection form for Pierce Sanders, Eliza Sanders, George Sanders, and Katy Sanders
- Postcard to Dr. J. E. Copeland; prescriptions by Dr. E. V. Copeland and Metcalf, N.D., 1 TDS, 5 TNS (Box-folder 01-033)
  J. E. Copeland is thanked in the postcard. Dr. E V. Copeland's prescriptions show his address as Round Hill, Va. His pharmacist was H. T. Morrison & Co. also from Round Hill. A fifth prescription is signed metcalf and written on a paper with J. P. Wyer, Druggist, No. 4 Culpeper Street, Warrenton, Va.
- Fragment of daybook of Dr. Bartholomew Enderson, 1804, 1979, 1 AD, 1 ANS, 1 TLS, 3 AN copies, 1 envelope (Box-folder 01-034)
  The daybook notes that Enderson died September 19, 1804 and was buried October 14.
- Daybook of Dr. J. E. Copeland, 1900-03, 1 AMS, newspaper clippings (Box-folder 01-035)
  The daybook lists Copeland's patients, and sometimes their their ailments and his charges.
- Dr. William P. Braxton's lecture cards from medical courses at the University of Pennsylvania, 1836-37, 14 DS (Box-folder 01-036)
  The cards are for lectures in surgery, chemistry, theory and practice of medicine and clinical practice, materia medica and pharmacy, anatomy, women and children, institutes of medicine at the University of Pennsylvania. One card indicates he paid $10 for the use of the Pennsylvania Hospital and was entitled to the privilege of attending the practice thereof and the use of the library for one year. One card is from the Philadelphia Medical Institute and relates to winter examinations.
- Account book kept by [Dr.?] Robert Gamble, 1834-39, 1 account book, 1 TD 1p. (Box-folder 01-037)
  The account book mentions medicine given and medical services rendered as well as nonmedical transactions for labor, food or sundry items. The description of the account book is listed in a sale document which states that Charlottesville and spring Hill are mentioned as is Augusta County. The account book was purchased from Bookworm & Silverfish, box 516, Wytheville, Va. 24382 on 2/3/82 for $35.
- Letter from W. W. Keen to Dr. J. O. Skinner, 1927 January 25, 1 TLS 1p. (Box-folder 01-038)
  The letter from Keen is to one of his students from 60 years earlier. He mentions having served in the Civil War and also encourages Skinner to read his book entitled "I Believe in God and in Evolution." Keen was a Professor of Surgery at the Jefferson Medical College in Philadelphia. The letter was given in February 1984 as a gift from Nell Fuller of the Acquisitions Department at the CMHSL.
- Letter from Howard A. Kelly to Doctor Morton, 1928 June 20, 1 TLS 1p. (Box-folder 01-039)
  Kelly thanks Morton for his monograph on peptic ulcer and says Morton could be seen at the private hospital where Kelly works. The letter was given in February 1984 as a gift from Nell Fuller of the Acquisitions Department at the CMHSL.
- "Women Medical Students at UVA, Notes of Janet Coleman Kimbrough, M.D." 1978 March 15, 1 TD 33pp. (Box-folder 02-001)
  This is Kimbrough's account of experiences as women in the Medical School at the time when women students were first admitted. Kimbrough was in the class of 1926. A number of professors are mentioned including R. Bennett Bean, Carl Speidel, Harvey E. Jordan, Harry T. Marshall, Gregory F. Lukianoff, Theodore Hough, James A. Waddell, John Staige Davis, "Burley" Watts, and James Carroll Flippin. Kimbrough describes courses in the various year, living arrangements and the search for internships.
- "Women Medical Students at UVA, Additions by Thelma Dunn, M.D." N.D., 1 TD 26pp. (Box-folder 02-002)
  This is Dean's account of experiences as women in the Medical School at the time when women students were first admitted. Dunn was in the class of 1926. She writes about Ruth Dean, the first woman to graduate from the School of Medicine at UVa. Professors that are mentioned include James A. Waddell, Harry T. Marshall, John Staige Davis, "Burley" Watts, R. Bennett Bean, Harvey E. Jordan, Theodore Hough, John S. Lawrence, Alfred Chanutin, James Carroll Flippin, Henry b. Mulholland, J. Edwin Wood, William H. Goowin, Isaac A. Bigger, John H. Neff, Allen F. Voshell, Royster, William E. Bray, D. C. Smith, William A. Lambeth, George B. Young, Paul B. Barringer, and Kenneth F. Maxcy. She also includes three stories about distinguished visitors to the University: William M. Thackeray, [Charles] Dickens, and Teddy Roosevelt.
- Letter from Thelma B. Dunn to Terry Thorkildson, "Women Medical Students at UVA," "Women Medical Students at UVA, Additions by Thelma Dunn, M.D.," and Notes of Janet Coleman Kimbrough, M.D. 1979 July 8 and N.D., 1 TLS 2pp., 2 TMs with AN 36pp. and 29pp., 1 AM 14 pp. (Box-folder 02-003)
  Dr. Themla Brumfield Dunn and Dr. Janet Coleman Kimbrough were requested by Mrs. Ferrell of the Medical Alumni Staff to write some account of their experiences as women in the Medical School at the time when women students were first admitted. Each of them first wrote an independent account of the events they remembered most vividly. They then got together and reduced the material to a brief account that the Medical Alumni News might wish to publish. These were given in February 1983 as a gift from Nell Fuller of the Acquisitions Department at the CMHSL.
- Documents related to the merger of the medical and nursing libraries, 1972 September-October, 1 TLS 1p., 5 Tmemos 10pp. (Box-folder 02-004)
  Participants in the process of library merger meetings include Wilhelm Moll, Nell Fuller, Thelma Moomaw, Ray Frantz, Kenneth Peterson, Phyllis Verhonick, and J. Robert Henderson. A letter is written from Ken Crispell to Wilhelm Moll.
- Letter from Christopher Bartels to Terry Thorkildson and letter from Terry Thorkildson to Christopher Bartels, 1988 June 6, 9, 2 TLS 3pp. (Box-folder 02-005)
  The letters regard a print of Walter Reed given by Dr. Robert Carey to the Mulholland Society to put in the renovated student lounge. The Mulholland Society wants to donate it to the library with the stipulation that it be publicly displayed.
- Letter from James R. Berry to Terry Thorkildson, 1983 October 31, 1 TLS 1p. (Box-folder 02-006)
  Berry thanks Thorkildson for the loan of the portrait of Thomas Jefferson.
- Letter from Edmund Berkeley to John Patruno and letter from John Patruno to Julius Barclay, 1989 March 29, April 11, 1 TLS 1p., 1 TLS copy 2pp. (Box-folder 02-007)
  The letters concern books that Joan Echtenkamp identified in Special Collections that would be of interest to Health Sciences.
- Letter from Harriet S. Craghead to Linda Watson and letter from Linda Watson to Harriet S. Craghead, 1993, November 1, 4, 1 TLS 2pp., 1 TLS copy 2pp. (Box-folder 02-008)
- Convocation comments by William Bennett Bean, 1950 January, 1 pamphlet (Box-folder 02-009)
  Bean's remarks were made at the opening convocation of the Colleges of Dentistry, Medicine and Pharmacy and the School of Nursing of the State University of Iowa, September 21, 1949.
- Invitation to the formal dedication of the Wilhelm Moll Rare Book and Medical History Room, 1981 May 14, 1 card, 1 envelope (Box-folder 02-010)
- University of Vriginia Medical Center 1961-1983 Department of Employee Health Services, 1985, January 30, 1 TD (Box-folder 02-011)
  In addition to being a handbook to Employee Health, the document includes material related to Nuzhet O. Atuk, Medical Director of the Employee Health Department from 1961-1983. A resolution honoring Atuk, copies of newletter articles, photos, and a letter regarding budgetary needs are included. Donated by Atuk on October 22, 2002.
- Nuzhet O. Atuk thank you from the McCoy family, N.D., 1 Typed certificate copy 1p. (Box-folder 02-012)
  The Mccoy family thanks Atuk for his work on Von Hippel-Lindau disease. Donated by Atuk on January 15, 2002.
- "Beginning of hemodialysis at the University of Virginia Hospital, 1959," N.D., 1 TMs with photos, 3 B&W, 1 color (Box-folder 02-013)
  The hemodialysis team consisted of Drs. N. O. Atuk, Graham Henson, and Alfon Mosca plus two nurses, Margaret Jordan and Elise Michael. Donated by Atuk on January 15, 2002.
- Letter from Nuzhet O. Atuk to George E. Schreiner and reply, 1959 April, 2 TLS copies 3pp. (Box-folder 02-014)
  Atuk's letter gives details on his first dialysis of a patient at UVa. Donated by Atuk on January 15, 2002. Donated by Atuk on January 15, 2002.
- Letter from A. C. Vanella to Dr. N. O. Atuk, 1959 June 9, 1 TLS 1 p. (Box-folder 02-015)
  Donated by Atuk on January 15, 2002.
- Letter from William Parson to Nuzhet Atuk, 1959 November 2, 1 TLS copy 1p. (Box-folder 02-016)
  Parson asks Atuk to write out the amount of money needed for the artificial kidney unit. Donated by Atuk on January 15, 2002.
- Letter from Nuzhet O. Atuk to William Parson, 1959 December 29, 1 TLS copy 2pp. (Box-folder 02-017)
  Atuk estimates costs needed to make an artificial kidney unit functional. Donated by Atuk on January 15, 2002.
- Letter from Robert T. Ulsh to William Parson, 1960 September 9, 1 TLS 1p. (Box-folder 02-018)
- Letter from Nuzhet O. Atuk to Robert T. Ulsh, 1960 september 23, 1 TL carbon 1p. (Box-folder 02-019)
- Floor plans for Dr. Atuk's room and kidney room, 1961 August 28, floor plans 2pp. (Box-folder 02-020)
- Letter from Grahame Henson to Nuzhet Atuk, 1995 July 31, 1 TLS copy 1p. (Box-folder 02-021)
- Letter from Charles H. Gleason to Nuzhet [O. Atuk], 1998 October 10, 1 ALS 1p. (Box-folder 02-022)
  Gleason remembers the excitement when UVa's first dialysis patient came out of her coma. Donated by Atuk on January 15, 2002.
- Letter from Florence Farrow to [Terry] Thorkildson enclosing a copy "The Cure of Cancer of the Breast by de Houppeville Translated from the French by Arthur S. Caron, M.D., 1981 October 10, 1 ALS 1p., 1 TM 20pp., 1 TD 1p. (Box-folder 02-023)
  Caron's translation is of part of Guillaume de Houppeville's book "La guerison du cancer au sein" printed in 1693. A Virgo record of the book is included.
- Correspondence between James S. Kennan and Mrs. Austin C. Embrey and Mrs. Leslie A. Faudree, 1989 June 6, 2 TLS copies 2pp., 1 TN copy 1p. (Box-folder 02-024)
  The correspondence regards the gift of the diploma of James Clayton Reed (Walter Reed's older brother) to HC&S and the burial place of the mother of Walter Reed, Pharaba.
- Correspondence between Jefferson Randolph Kean and Joan Echtenkamp Klein, 1989 November, 1 TLS copy 2pp., 1 TLS 1p. (Box-folder 02-025)
  The correspondence regards the location of Kean's grandfather's diaries at Special Collections rather than HC&S.
- "The Daily Progress" University of Virginia Special Sesquicentennial Edition, 1969 April 13, 5 newspaper clippings copies 7pp. (Box-folder 02-026)
  The articles are about the University of Virginia Medical Center, School of Medicine and a brief history of the University of Virginia.
- Physician's recipe book, James Mills, 1822 Dec. 29 - 1824 Sept. 24, 1 book, 23 leaves (Box-folder 02-027)
  This little book has recipes for curing people with the following complaints: ague, cough, cold, ulcer, swollen glands, swollen legs, night sweats, cuts, sores, bruises, green sores, whooping cough, and erysipelas, as well as one for strengthening a person recovering from sickness. Also included are recipes for horses, sheep, and cows. It has directions for making bottled porter, beer, blacking, waterproof blacking, polish, and explosives such as squibs and fulminating silver. The accompanying thank you letter is a copy of one sent to the donor, Victoria Menzies.
- Recipe book for medicines, food, and miscellaneous items, 1841-1867, 1 MSS book with newspaper clippings (Box-folder 02-028)
  This book has directions for killing insects, planting fruit trees, making black ink and tallow candles, washing, and making or preserving the following food items: candy, cider, beef, ice cream, cabbage pickle, yeast, wine, mead, catsup, and toffee. Some of treatments for diseases included are: bronchitis, whooping cough, earache, stomach cramps, effects of laudanum, wounds, scrofula, asthma, ague, fever, cold, carbuncle, dysentery, bowel complaint, cholera, diarrhea, night sweats, rheumatism, vomiting, rattlesnake bite, mad dog bite, lockjaw, burns, cholic, erysipelas, croup, deafness, consumption, cancer, dropsy, piles, sore eyes, and quincy. Directions for the treatment of horses are included. The book is the gift of Miss Thomasia Goss, Comyn Hall, 601 Park St. Charlottesville, 22901, and was found in a trunk at the family home near Stoney Point. It was brought to the library by R. M. Hubbard, a retired UVa Engineering faculty member.
- Medical College of Virginia final examination: physical diagnosis, 1921 May 26, 1 TD (Box-folder 02-029)
- Letter soliciting support for expansion of UVa hospital from Vincent W. Archer and pamphlet with history and data from UVa and Virginia, [1945], 1 TL, pamphlet (Box-folder 02-030)
- Memoirs Medical Alumni, Class of 1928 Univrsity of Virgiinia May 1978: Hubert B. Holsinger, 1978 May, 1 TD photocopy (Box-folder 02-031)
  Holsinger writes about his family, medical training, time with the 8th Evac, and later life.
- Letter from William H. Muller to Mark Ravitch, [pre 1964?], 1 TL photocopy, 1 business card (Box-folder 02-032)
  Muller writes about his memories of Dr. Alfred Blalock. The letter was found in Dr. Muller's office by Wayne W. Ferguson.
- Floor plans of the Claude Moore Medical Education Building, 2009, 1 floor plan photocopy (Box-folder 02-033)
- UVa Internal Medicine: A Century of Excellence by Munsey S. Wheby, 2007, May 5, 2 TMs (1 with AN)photocopies, 1 PowerPoint print out (Box-folder 02-034)
  Wheby gives the highlights of the Department of Medicine and includes pictures of buildings and prominent people in the department.